Guide to the Senegal Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Senegal collection
1816-2013
1816-1991
MS 1539
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of printed material and ephemera relating to historical, political, social, and economic conditions in Senegal.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed material and ephemera relating to historical, political, social, and economic conditions in Senegal.
Women -- Senegal; Senegal -- Politics and government; Senegal -- Social conditions; Sengegal -- Economic conditions
- Original Accession
  - Certificate authorizing payment to the next of kin of Samuel Bruell, private in the Royal African Regiment of Infantry, deceased; printed document with details of vessels and slaves captured, 1816 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jalons, Revue d'Afrique Noire, 1942 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Les Sénégalais sout appelés dimanche à approuver le projet de Constitution presenté par M. Senghor," par Ernest Milcent, Le Monde, 1963 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers (without political affiliations), 1972, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
  - Ministère de l'Information: magazines, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rapport d'Activités": report of the Office Sénégalais de l'Artisanat, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Disóó: Bulletin périodique du service de la Radio Éducative," Ministère de l'Information et des Télécommunications, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Forces Armées Sénégalaises: bulletins, [1974?], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women's magazines, 1976, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Centre Sénégalais du Commerce Extérieur: pamphlet, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1980, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Momsarev: publication of the Parti Africain de l'Indépendance (P.A.I. Sénégal), 1980 November (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Political journals, 1980, 1986, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Parti Démocratique Sénégalais (P.D.S.): feminist journals, newspapers, printed materials, 1980, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Educational/academic journals, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ligue Démocratique/Mouvement pour le Parti du Travail (LD/MPT): news bulletins, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Parti de l'Indépendance et du Travail (PIT-Sénégal): bulletins, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Union pour la Démocratie Populaire (U.D.P.): news magazine, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Mouvement National des Jeunesses Socialistes: newspapers, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Parti Socialiste (PS): newspapers, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The African Cultural Institute: magazines, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Le Cafard Magazine: mensuel d'informations générales et de loisirs, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - And Jëf/Mouvement Révolutionnaire pour la Démocratie Nouvelle (M.R.D.N.): newspapers, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Les Enfants Martyrs, revue d'information de formation et de défense des enfants, 1990 Apr/May (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Parti pour la Libération du Peuple (PLP): newspapers, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Le Travailleur Salarie: bulletin d'information et d'écho des luttes des travailleurs, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - International Committee for the Defense of African Workers (ICDAW): printed materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-030
  - Additional printed materials, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-054
  - Letter from President Leopold Senghor of Senegal to Professor Leonard Thompson [re possibility of sending Senegalese students to UCLA], 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Badolo-Bi [Organe de La Section de France du Parti Africain de L'Indépendance], [1980?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Haï" [booklet on poetry from Cercle des Poetes], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Pour Une Formation à Distance en Education Environnementale" [pamphlet from Programme Régional de Formation-Information pour L'Enviro (PFIE/SUD)], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-087
  - Publications
    - BLIBAD: Bullétin de Liaison à L'intention des Bibliothecaires, Archivistes et Documentalistes Africains, 1976 Jan, 1981 Mai (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - L'étudiant sénégalais: Journal d'information et d'opinion de l'Association des Etudiants Sénégalais en France (A.E.S.F.), no. 1, Circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business advertising cards, 1889, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1944-1992; Accession 2010-M-080
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged as received.
  - Palabre: Organe de Liaison Entre la Direction des Lettres et les Centres Culturels Régionaux, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vive le Marxisme-Léninisme!, no. 8, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armée Nation: revue des forces armées sénégalaises, no. 5, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Solidarité: revue trimestrielle africaine d'information sur les personnes handicapées, no. 1, 1985 January-March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Our Rights, vol. 1, no. 4, Africa Regional Steering Committee for the Dakar/Beijing Conference on Women, 1944 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Les Enfants Martyrs, no. 12, (Hope Unlimited-Espoir sans Frontières), 1992 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Degoo: le mensuel africain du développement, no. 2, 1985 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MOMSAREEW: Organe du Parti Africain de L'indépendance, (21st anniversary), 5e série, no. 7, 1978 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MOMSAREEW: Organe du Parti Africain de L'indépendance (Special Congrès), no. 11, 1979 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - La Lutte: Organe du Parti Africain de L'Indépendance, 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Le Mutant d'Afrique: trimestriel d'information culturelle et scientifique, no. 1, 1982 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Waraango: arts-culture-société, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Loose page entitled "Conclusion" pertaining to the revolutionary movement, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vérité: organe politique de formation et d'information, 1982 March-April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Combat Pour Le Socialisme, 1987 Sep, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diamono Le Temps: tribune africaine de l'économie et de l'analyse sociale, no 2, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - L'indépendant, no. 1, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Djamra: revue sénégalaise des dossiers sociaux, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - L'Action Patriotique, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Action Islamique, no. 1, 1985 December-1986 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - La Lanterne: mensuel d'informations analytiques aux tribunes libres, no. 2, 1984 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Le Défi: Organe d'Informations et d'Analyses, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Le Rénovateur: Organe du Parti Démocratique du Sénégal Rénovation (PDS/Renovation), no. 1, 1987 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tout Plus: le magazine du développement, 1988 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sud Hebdo, no. 6, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - La Nation, no. 2, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Muntu Dimanche, 1985 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional material, 1960-2013; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1960-2013 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Campaign button, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Posters, Circa 2000-2012 (Folder 2)